[
  {
    "question": "Where were the Ghadar revolutionaries, who became active\nduring the outbreak of World war\nbased\n(a)\nCentral America\n(b)\nNorth America\n(c)\nWest America\n(d)\nSouth America",
    "choices": "(a)\nCentral America\n(b)\nNorth America\n(c)\nWest America\n(d)\nSouth America",
    "answer": "(b) North America",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "With\nreference\nto\nthe\nperiod\nof\nextremist\nnationalist\nmovement in India with its spirit f Swadeshi, which one of the\nfollowing statements is not correct?\n(a)\nLiaqat Hossian led the Muslim peasants of Barisal in their\nagitations\n(b)\nIn\n1898,\nthe\nscheme\nof\nnational\neducation\nwas\nformulated by Satish Chandra Mukherjee\n(c)\nThe Bengal National College\nwas founded in\n1906 with\nAurobindo as the principal\n(d)\nTagore preached the cult of Atmashakti, the main plan of\nwhich\nwas the\nsocial and\neconomic regeneration\nof the\nvillages.",
    "choices": "(a)\nLiaqat Hossian led the Muslim peasants of Barisal in their\nagitations\n(b)\nIn\n1898,\nthe\nscheme\nof\nnational\neducation\nwas\nformulated by Satish Chandra Mukherjee\n(c)\nThe Bengal National College\nwas founded in\n1906 with\nAurobindo as the principal\n(d)\nTagore preached the cult of Atmashakti, the main plan of\nwhich\nwas the\nsocial and\neconomic regeneration\nof the\nvillages.",
    "answer": "(a) Liaqat Hossian led the Muslim peasants of Barisal\nin their agitations",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following were the main influences on Vasudeo\nBalvant Phadke?\n1. Experience of the Deccan famine of 1876-77\n2. Hindu revivalism\n3.Theory of Drain of Wealth\n4.The reformist idea of Phule\nSelect the correct answer\nusing the code given below :\na) 1,2 and 3\nb)2,3 and 4\nc) 1 and 3 only\nd) 2 and 4 only",
    "choices": "a) 1,2 and 3\nb)2,3 and 4\nc) 1 and 3 only\nd) 2 and 4 only",
    "answer": "(a) 1, 2 and 3",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about Sir Syed Ahmad Khan\nis/are correct?\n1.He\nargued\nthat\nIndia\nwas\na\nfederation\nof\nethnic\ncommunities based on common descent.\n2. His   philosophy\nwas\nvery\nsimilar\nto\nthat\nof\nthe\nIndian\nNational Congress.\n3.He imagined India\nas\na\nNation State based\non individual\ncitizen's rights.\n4.The curriculum at the Mohammedan Anglo-Oriental College\nblended Muslim theology and European empiricism:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\na) 1 only\nb) 2and3\nc) 3 only\nd) 1 and 4",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\nb) 2and3\nc) 3 only\nd) 1 and 4",
    "answer": "(d) 1 and 4",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "With\nreference\nto\nthe\nbook\n'Desher\nKatha'\nwritten\nby\nSakharam\nGanesh\nDeuskar   during\nthe\nfreedom\nstruggle,\nconsider the following statements:\n1.It warned against the Colonial State's hypnotic conquest of\nthe mind.\n2.It inspired the performance of swadeshi\nstreet plays and\nfolk songs.\n3.The use of 'desh' by Deuskar was in the specific context of\nthe region of Bengal:\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\n(a)\n1 and 2 only\n(b)\n2 and 3 only\n(c)\n1 and 3 only\n(d)\n1,2 and 3",
    "choices": "(a)\n1 and 2 only\n(b)\n2 and 3 only\n(c)\n1 and 3 only\n(d)\n1,2 and 3",
    "answer": "(a) 1 and 2 only",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "After the First World War; the Triveni Sangh was formed by\na)the Jats and Gujjars\nbJthe Rajputs and Yadavs\nc)the Jats and Yadavs\nd)the Ahirs and Kurmis",
    "choices": "a)the Jats and Gujjars\nbJthe Rajputs and Yadavs\nc)the Jats and Yadavs\nd)the Ahirs and Kurmis",
    "answer": "(d) the Ahirs and Kurmis",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "\nConsider the following freedom fighters:\na) Barindra Kumar Ghosh\nb)Jogesh Chandra Chatterjee\nc) Rash Behari Bose\nWho\nof the\nabove was/were actively\nassociated with\nthe\nGhadar Party?\n(a)\n1 and 2\n(b)\n2 only\n(c)\n1 and 3\n(d)\n3 only",
    "choices": "(a)\n1 and 2\n(b)\n2 only\n(c)\n1 and 3\n(d)\n3 only",
    "answer": "(d) 3 only",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who founded the 'Seva Samiti at Allahabad in 1914?\na) Hridayanath Kunzru\nb)G. K: Gokhale\nc) Shri Ram Bajpai\nd)T: B. Sapru",
    "choices": "a) Hridayanath Kunzru\nb)G. K: Gokhale\nc) Shri Ram Bajpai\nd)T: B. Sapru",
    "answer": "(a) Hridayanath Kunzru",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Partition of Bengal made by Lord Curzon in 1905 lasted\nuntil\n(a)\nthe First World War when Indian troops were needed\nby the British and the partition was ended:\n(b)\nKing George\nV\nabrogated\nCurzon's\nAct\nat\nthe Royal\nDurbar in Delhi in 1911.\n(c)\nGandhiji launched his Civil Disobedience\nMovement:\n(d)\nthe Partition of India in 1947 when East Bengal became\nEast Pakistan.",
    "choices": "(a)\nthe First World War when Indian troops were needed\nby the British and the partition was ended:\n(b)\nKing George\nV\nabrogated\nCurzon's\nAct\nat\nthe Royal\nDurbar in Delhi in 1911.\n(c)\nGandhiji launched his Civil Disobedience\nMovement:\n(d)\nthe Partition of India in 1947 when East Bengal became\nEast Pakistan.",
    "answer": "(b) King George V abrogated Curzon's Act at the Royal\nDurbar in Delhi in 1911",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A\nLondon\nbranch\nof\nthe\nAII\nIndia\nMuslim\nLeague\nwas\nestablished in 1908 under the presidency of\n(a)\nAga Khan\n(b)\nAmeer Ali\n(c)\nLiyaqat Ali Khan\n(d)\nMs\nA. Jinnah",
    "choices": "(a)\nAga Khan\n(b)\nAmeer Ali\n(c)\nLiyaqat Ali Khan\n(d)\nMs\nA. Jinnah",
    "answer": "(b) Ameer Ali",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which member of the Servants of India Society founded the\nSeva Samiti at Allahabad in 1914?\na) Shri Ram Bajpai\nb)Hriday Nath Kunzru\nc) S. G. Vaze\nd)Srinivas Shastri",
    "choices": "a) Shri Ram Bajpai\nb)Hriday Nath Kunzru\nc) S. G. Vaze\nd)Srinivas Shastri",
    "answer": "(b) Hriday Nath Kunzru",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following is the author of the autobiography\nAamar Katha (1913)?\na) Satyajit\nb)Rassundari Devi\nc) Ganesh Chandra Ghosh\nd)Binodini Dasi",
    "choices": "a) Satyajit\nb)Rassundari Devi\nc) Ganesh Chandra Ghosh\nd)Binodini Dasi",
    "answer": "(d) Binodini Dasi",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements\n1.B. G. Tilak founded the Home Rule League in April 1916 in\nMaharashtra.\n2.N.\nC. Kelkar\nwas\nnot\nassociated\nwith\nthe\nHome\nRule\nMovement:\nWhich of the statements above is/are correct?\na) 1 only\nb)2 only\nc) Both 1 and 2\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\nb)2 only\nc) Both 1 and 2\nd)Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "(a) 1 only",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ray\nFour resolutions were passed at the famous Calcutta session of\nIndian\nNational\nCongress\nin\n1906.\nThe question\nof\neither\nretention or of\nrejection of these four resolutions became the\ncause of split in Congress at the next congress session held in\nSurat in\n1907 .\nWhich of the following was\nnot\none of those\nresolutions?\n(a)\nAnnulment of Partition of Bengal\n(b)\nBoycott\n(c)\nNational Education\n(d)\nSwadeshi",
    "choices": "(a)\nAnnulment of Partition of Bengal\n(b)\nBoycott\n(c)\nNational Education\n(d)\nSwadeshi",
    "answer": "(a) Annulment of Partition of Bengal",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the context of the Indian freedom struggle, 16 October 1905\nis well known for which of the following reasons?\n(a)\nThe formal proclamation of the Swadeshi movement was\nmade in Calcutta Town Hall:\n(b)\nPartition of Bengal took effect:\n(c)\nDadabhai Naoroji declared that the goal of the Indian\nNational Congress was Swaraj:\n(d)\nLokmanaya\nTilak\nstarted\nthe\nSwadeshi\nmovement\nin\nPoona:",
    "choices": "(a)\nThe formal proclamation of the Swadeshi movement was\nmade in Calcutta Town Hall:\n(b)\nPartition of Bengal took effect:\n(c)\nDadabhai Naoroji declared that the goal of the Indian\nNational Congress was Swaraj:\n(d)\nLokmanaya\nTilak\nstarted\nthe\nSwadeshi\nmovement\nin\nPoona:",
    "answer": "(b) Partition of Bengal took effect",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The headquarters of the Ghadar Movement/Party were at\na) San Francisco\nb)Stanford University\nc) Portland\nd)Florida",
    "choices": "a) San Francisco\nb)Stanford University\nc) Portland\nd)Florida",
    "answer": "(a) San Francisco",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following\nwas\none\nof the founders\nof the\nIndian Society of Oriental Art?\na) Rabindranath Tagore\nb)Abanindranath Tagore\nc) Dwarakanath Tagore\nd)Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyaya",
    "choices": "a) Rabindranath Tagore\nb)Abanindranath Tagore\nc) Dwarakanath Tagore\nd)Bankim Chandra Chattopadhyaya",
    "answer": "(b) Abanindranath Tagore",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following had organised, in 1904,\na\nsecret\nsociety of revolutionaries named Abhinav Bharat?\na) Khudiram Bose\nb)Shyamji Krishna Verma\nc) Har Dayal\nd) VD Savarkar",
    "choices": "a) Khudiram Bose\nb)Shyamji Krishna Verma\nc) Har Dayal\nd) VD Savarkar",
    "answer": "(d) V D Savarkar",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following formed the Seva Samiti\nScouts\nAssociation in 1914?\na) Hriday Nath Kunzru\nb)S. G. Vaze\nc) Annie Besant\nd)Shri Ram Bajpai",
    "choices": "a) Hriday Nath Kunzru\nb)S. G. Vaze\nc) Annie Besant\nd)Shri Ram Bajpai",
    "answer": "(d) Shri Ram Bajpai",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Boy\nThe year 1916 is important in Indian history for:\n1. Lucknow Session of the Congress\n2.Congress\nLeague Pact\n3. Formation of Home Rule League\nSelect the correct answer using the code given\na) 1 and 3\nb)2 and 3 only\nc) 1 and 2 only\nd)1, 2 and 3",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 3\nb)2 and 3 only\nc) 1 and 2 only\nd)1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "(d) 1,2 and 3",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who\namong\nthe\nfollowing\npioneering\nBengali\nwomen\nserialised her autobiography Amar Katha between\n1910 and\n1913?\na) Binodini Dasi\nb)Rashsundari Debi\nc) Begum Rokeya Sakhawat Hossain\nd) Kailashbashini Debi",
    "choices": "a) Binodini Dasi\nb)Rashsundari Debi\nc) Begum Rokeya Sakhawat Hossain\nd) Kailashbashini Debi",
    "answer": "(a) Binodini Dasi",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "only\nWith\nreference\nto\nthe\nSwadeshi\nMovement,\nconsider\nthe\nfollowing statements:\n1.It contributed to the revival of the indigenous artisan crafts\nand industries.\n2. The National Council of Education was established as a part\nof the Swadeshi Movement:\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?\n(a)\n1 only\n2 only\nTG\nBoth 1 and 2\nNeither 1 nor 2",
    "choices": "(a)\n1 only\n2 only\nTG\nBoth 1 and 2\nNeither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "He\nwrote\nbiographies\nof\nMazzini;, Garibaldi;\nShivaji\nand\nShrikrishna, stayed in\nAmerica for some time; and\nwas also\nelected to the\nCentral Assembly: He was:\n(a)\nAurobindo Ghosh\n(b)\nBipin Chandra Pal\n(c)\nLala Lajpat Rai\n(d)\nMotilal Nehru",
    "choices": "(a)\nAurobindo Ghosh\n(b)\nBipin Chandra Pal\n(c)\nLala Lajpat Rai\n(d)\nMotilal Nehru",
    "answer": "(c) Lala Lajpat Rai",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Ghadr (Ghadar) was a\n(a)\nRevolutionary\nAssociation\nof\nIndians,\nwith\nheadquarters in San Francisco\n(b)\nNationalist organisation operating from Singapore\n(c)\nMilitant organisation with headquarters in Berlin\n(d)\nCommunist\nmovement\nfor\nIndia's\nfreedom\nwith\nheadquarters at Tashkent",
    "choices": "(a)\nRevolutionary\nAssociation\nof\nIndians,\nwith\nheadquarters in San Francisco\n(b)\nNationalist organisation operating from Singapore\n(c)\nMilitant organisation with headquarters in Berlin\n(d)\nCommunist\nmovement\nfor\nIndia's\nfreedom\nwith\nheadquarters at Tashkent",
    "answer": "(a)\nRevolutionary\nAssociation\nOf\nIndians;\nwith\nheadquarters in San Francisco",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the immediate cause for the launch of the Swadeshi\nMovement?\n(a)\nThe partition of Bengal done by Lord Curzon\n(b)\nA\nsentence\nof\n18\nmonths\nrigorous\nimprisonment\nimposed on Lokmanya Tilak\n(c)\nThe\narrest and deportation\nof\nLala Lajpat\nRai and\nAjit\nSingh; and the passing f the Punjab colonisation bill\n(d)\nDeath sentence pronounced on the Chapekar brothers",
    "choices": "(a)\nThe partition of Bengal done by Lord Curzon\n(b)\nA\nsentence\nof\n18\nmonths\nrigorous\nimprisonment\nimposed on Lokmanya Tilak\n(c)\nThe\narrest and deportation\nof\nLala Lajpat\nRai and\nAjit\nSingh; and the passing f the Punjab colonisation bill\n(d)\nDeath sentence pronounced on the Chapekar brothers",
    "answer": "(a) The partition of Bengal done by Lord Curzon",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nof the\nfollowing are true in the context of Swadeshi\nmovement in 1905?\n1. Massive demonstrations were held in Bengal\n2. Hartal was observed in Calcutta\n3. The\nmovement\nwas initiated\nby the\nmoderates\nbut\nwas\ntaken over by the revolutionary nationalists at a later stage\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\na) 1,2 and 3\nb)1 and 2 only\nc) 2 and 3 only\nd) 1 and 3 only",
    "choices": "a) 1,2 and 3\nb)1 and 2 only\nc) 2 and 3 only\nd) 1 and 3 only",
    "answer": "(a) 1, 2 and 3",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about Prarthana Samaj are\ncorrect?\n1.Its aim was to reform the Hindu society\n2.It was based in Maharashtra\n3.It believed in monotheism\n4.It had greatly influenced the Brahmo Samaj\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\na) 1 and 2 only\nb)2 and 3 only\nc) 1, 2 and 3\nd)1 and 4",
    "choices": "a) 1 and 2 only\nb)2 and 3 only\nc) 1, 2 and 3\nd)1 and 4",
    "answer": "(c) 1, 2 and 3",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why was Vasudeo Balwant Phadke known in history?\na)He led a violent struggle against the British during the revolt\nof 1857\nb)He was a critic of Gandhian struggle\nc) He led an armed uprising against the British in the 1870s\nd)He was a radical leader of the Indian National Congress",
    "choices": "a)He led a violent struggle against the British during the revolt\nof 1857\nb)He was a critic of Gandhian struggle\nc) He led an armed uprising against the British in the 1870s\nd)He was a radical leader of the Indian National Congress",
    "answer": "(c) He led an armed uprising against the British in the\n1870s",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In 1920, which of the following changed its name to \"Swarajya\nSabha\"?\n(a)\nAll India Home Rule League\nHindu Mahasabha\nTG\nSouth Indian Liberal Federation\nThe Servants of India Society",
    "choices": "(a)\nAll India Home Rule League\nHindu Mahasabha\nTG\nSouth Indian Liberal Federation\nThe Servants of India Society",
    "answer": "(a) All India Home Rule League",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the main reason for the split in the Indian National\nCongress at Surat in 1907?\n(a)\nIntroduction\nof communalism\ninto\nIndian politics by\nLord Minto.\n(b)\nExtremists'\nlack\nof\nfaith\nin\nthe\ncapacity\nof\nthe\nmoderates to negotiate with the\nBritish Government:\n(c)\nFoundation of Muslim League.\n(d)\nAurobindo\nGhosh's\ninability\nto\nbe\nelected\nas\nthe\npresident of the Indian National Congress",
    "choices": "(a)\nIntroduction\nof communalism\ninto\nIndian politics by\nLord Minto.\n(b)\nExtremists'\nlack\nof\nfaith\nin\nthe\ncapacity\nof\nthe\nmoderates to negotiate with the\nBritish Government:\n(c)\nFoundation of Muslim League.\n(d)\nAurobindo\nGhosh's\ninability\nto\nbe\nelected\nas\nthe\npresident of the Indian National Congress",
    "answer": "(b)\nExtremists' lack of faith in\nthe capacity of the\nmoderates to negotiate with the British Government",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following\na\nsystematic critique of the\nmoderate politics of the Indian National Congress in a series of\narticles entitled New Lamps for Old?\n(a)\nAurobindo Ghosh\n(b)\nR.C. Dutt\n(c)\nSyed Ahmed Khan\n(d)\nViraghavachariar",
    "choices": "(a)\nAurobindo Ghosh\n(b)\nR.C. Dutt\n(c)\nSyed Ahmed Khan\n(d)\nViraghavachariar",
    "answer": "(a) Aurobindo Ghosh",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The song\n'Amar\nSonar Bangla'\nwritten during the Swadeshi\nmovement\nof\nIndia\ninspired\nthe\nliberation\nstruggle\nof\nBangladesh\nand\nwas\nadopted\nas\nthe\nNational\nAnthem\nof\nBangladesh: Who wrote this song?\n(a)\nRajni Kanta Sen\n(b)\nDwijendra lal Ray\n(c)\nMukunda Das\n(d)\nRabindra Nath Tagore",
    "choices": "(a)\nRajni Kanta Sen\n(b)\nDwijendra lal Ray\n(c)\nMukunda Das\n(d)\nRabindra Nath Tagore",
    "answer": "(d) Rabindra Nath Tagore",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "gave\nThe 'Swadeshi'\nand 'Boycott'\nwere adopted\nas\nmethods\nof\nstruggle for the first time during the\n(a)\nAgitation against the partition of Bengal\nHome Rule Movement\nT\nNon-Cooperation Movement\nVisit of Simon Commission to India",
    "choices": "(a)\nAgitation against the partition of Bengal\nHome Rule Movement\nT\nNon-Cooperation Movement\nVisit of Simon Commission to India",
    "answer": "(a) Agitation against the partition of Bengal",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following movements has contributed to\na\nsplit in the Indian National Congress resulting in emergence\nof\n'moderates' and 'extremists'?\n(a)\nSwadeshi Movement\n(b)\nQuit India Movement\nNon-Cooperation Movement\n(d)\nCivil Disobedience Movement",
    "choices": "(a)\nSwadeshi Movement\n(b)\nQuit India Movement\nNon-Cooperation Movement\n(d)\nCivil Disobedience Movement",
    "answer": "(a) Swadeshi Movement",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\nof\nthe\nfollowing\nstatements\nabout\nthe\nSwadeshi\nmovement in Bengal in 1905 are correct?\n1.It\nwas\nmarked\nby\nthe\nmass\nmobilisation\nthrough\nthe\norganisation of \"Samitis\"\n2. It\nwas\nmarked by the\nmass\nmobilisation through\nlabour\nstrikes\n3.It\nadvocated\na\nconstructive\nprogramme\nof self-help\nor\n\"Atma shakti\"\n4.In\nthe\nsphere\nof\neducation,\nnational\nschools\nwere\nestablished\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\na) 1,2 and 3 only\nb)1 and 4 only\nc) 2,3 and 4 only\nd)1,2,3 and 4",
    "choices": "a) 1,2 and 3 only\nb)1 and 4 only\nc) 2,3 and 4 only\nd)1,2,3 and 4",
    "answer": "(d) 1,2,3 and 4",
    "topic": "The Nationalist Movement (1905-1918)"
  }
]